Guide to the Curt von Faber du Faur Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Curt von Faber du Faur papers
1936-1966
YCGL MSS 23
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.68
(27 boxes)
The collection consists of material generated by Curt von Faber du Faur as author, collector, literary historian, curator of the Yale Collection of German Literature, and Yale faculty member. Material comprises writings, including drafts of literary and critical works, articles, lectures, and essays; correspondence; and personal papers.
Faber du Faur, Curt von, 1890-1966
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Curt von Faber du Faur, 1966.
Custodial History
The bulk of the papers was left in the library when Faber died.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 26 and 27 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile materials. Regerence copies may be requested. Consult Access Serivices for further information.
Curt von Faber du Faur (1890-1966)
Curt von Faber du Faur, Yale professor and Curator of the Yale Collection of German Literature, was born in Stuttgart, Germany, on July 5, 1890. In 1958, he provided this biographical information on a questionnaire sent to him by the Yale University Press, which was about to issue the first volume of his catalog, German Baroque Literature.
"I was an officer in the German Army, from 1909-1919. Left January 1919, studied History of Art and German Literature at Munich and Giessen. Settled as an antiquarian in Munich 1923. Transferred my home to Florence, Italy, 1931. Lived there farming olives, wheat and wine. Wrote criticism and articles for "Frankfurter Zeitung". Emigrated to America, March, 1939. Was book collector since 1911. Offered my collection as a loan to Harvard University where it stood from 1939 to 1944. Lectured at Harvard. Sold the collection to Yale 1944. Became Research Associate, 1944, Research Professor February 1951."
A few facts may be added to this modest autobiographical sketch. On his father's side, Faber was descended from a distinguished military family and also from the French jurist and poet, Guy de Faur, seigneur de Pibrac (1529-84), a friend of Ronsard. Faber's mother was descended from the Cottas, publishers to Goethe and numerous other writers.
In the army, Faber held the rank of lieutenant; his discharge came about because of illness. After graduate study in Munich and Giessen, he was awarded his PhD in art history by the latter university. His dissertation, on a late fifteenth-century south German engraver and painter, was published as Der Hausbuchmeister (Berlin, Gloria-Verlag, 1921).
During the 1920s, he was in contact with the circle around the poet Stefan George, where he met his future wife, Emma Schabert, née Mock, widow of Rufus Blake. Their marriage took place in 1928. (The Yale Collection of German Literature counts among its holdings Faber's heavily annotated copies of George's poetry cycles.)
Faber's career as an antiquarian bookseller was distinguished. In 1923 he and Dr. Georg Karl founded the firm Karl & Faber in Munich, which grew to be one of Germany's major auction houses for antiquarian books and art. The firm still does business, after several name changes, as Hartung & Hartung. Among the early catalogs published by the Karl & Faber was Sammlung Victor Manheimer. Deutsche Barockliteratur von Opitz bis Brockes (Katalog 27, 1927), which Faber wrote with Karl Wolfskehl.
While "farming olives, wheat and wine" in Italy in the 1930s, Faber also wrote and published a volume of poetry and three Expressionist plays: Uffizien. 14 Gedichte (Florence, 1933); Das grüne Blut. Dramatisches Gedicht (Munich, 1936); Der Abfall. Dramatisches Gedicht (Munich, 1937), and St. Satyros. Dramatisches Gedicht (Munich, 1937).
Oral tradition at Yale has always maintained that Curt von Faber du Faur abandoned Harvard in favor of Yale because Harvard did not grant him faculty rank. (In the retained administrative files of the Yale Collection of German Literature, there is a folder of material documenting the actual negotiations between Yale and Faber.) At Yale, his initial appointment was as Research Associate in German Literature and Bibliography and Associate Curator of the German Literature Collection (Carl Schreiber was still curator of the Speck Collection at that time). By 1951 he had been promoted to Research Professor in German Literature and Bibliography and by 1955 he was sole curator of the library collection. During these years he held visiting lectureships at Columbia University (1949/50) and in the Middlebury College summer school (1951).
Faber was a fellow of Davenport College at Yale and a trustee of the Yale Library Associates. His major honors included the Yale Medal (1964), the Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of German ( Bundesverdienstkreuz, 1965), and the gold Goethe Medal of the Goethe Institut (1966). He was a member of the Deutsche Akademie für Sprache und Dichtung in Darmstadt. Among his friends were Richard Alewyn, Ernst Hauswedell, Paul Hindemith, Thornton Wilder, and Karl Wolfskehl.
Through his collecting, writing, and teaching, Curt von Faber du Faur envigorated the study of seventeenth-century German literature in the United States. The two-volume bibliography of his book collection was for a long time a standard bibliographical reference in the field of German baroque literature; its discursive chapter introductions still serve as a general introduction to the field. See "The Legacy of Curt Faber du Faur to the United States" ( Colloquia Germanica 25 [1992], 195–209) by Blake Lee Spahr, probably Faber's most prominent student.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material generated by Curt von Faber du Faur as author, collector, literary historian, curator of the Yale Collection of German Literature, and Yale faculty member. Material comprises writings, including drafts of literary and critical works, articles, lectures, and essays; correspondence; and personal papers.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series: I. Literary Works, 1930s. II. Books and Book Projects, 1936-1966. III. Graduate Courses: Lectures and Notes, 1949-1961. IV. Articles, Lectures, and Research Notes by Topic, 1946-1960. V. Correspondence. VI. Personal Papers. VII. Writings by Others.
Authors, German; Baroque literature -- Germany; Book collecting; German literature -- 18th century; German literature -- 19th century; German literature -- 20th Century; German literature -- Early modern, 1500-1700; Audiovisual materials; Videocassettes; Faber du Faur, Curt von, 1890-1966; Yale University -- Faculty
- Literary Works, 1930s; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  While the papers contain no material related to his earliest literary works, they do include a number of short stories and a full-length, unpublished novel ("Rah Rah Boy"), the theme of which suggests that the book was written after the author had gained some experience of Yale: during an ocean crossing to the United States, a European family meets a Yale football cheerleader, the Rah Rah Boy of the title.
  Related Archival Materials note
  The collection of Faber du Faur's papers at Stanford University (Collection M0562) contains an extensive fragment of another unpublished novel, "Schloss Rattenberg."
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Der Begleiter, carbon typescript, 42 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    This short story also forms a section of the novel Rah-Ray Boy.
  - Der Emigrant und das Fenster, autograph ms., 18 p. (short story) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Die falschen Laurenbergs, typescript, 51 p., with a few pages of corrected carbon copy (short story) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Poems], many of them photocopies from the files of Hermann J. Weigand (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rah Ray Boy, carbon typescript, with corrections, 638 p. (novel) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Der schwäbische Zorn, 2 different carbon typescripts, 10 and 11 p.; galley proof (short story) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tabula Rasa. Printed copy from Frankfurter Zeitung, (short story), 26 July 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Books and Book Projects, 1936-1966; Series II; 3.75; (9 boxes)
  In addition to his published volumes, Faber was working on a literary critical book about the baroque period, perhaps two books. "Die Maske in der Dichtung des 17. Jahrhunderts" is represented by three nearly completed chapters and an introduction; an outline found elsewhere in the papers and filed with the introduction suggests that he had at least some thoughts of pursuing the theme of masks through the Enlightenment era. The third chapter, "Ohne Larve," concerns Opitz's anti-war poem Trostgedicht, first published in 1633 but written probably around 1620. "Ohne Larve" seems also to be part of another book taking shape, one about Opitz, for which there are many notes, concepts, fragments, and drafts. There are points of tangency between this material and Faber's Germanic Review article "Monarch, patron and poet" (1949) and a close relationship with his PMLA article of 1954 on Opitz's Aristarchus, which may have been conceived as a chapter for the Opitz book. Faber tried to organize these materials in different ways. He appears to have reassembled parts and pieces from the unpublished book projects and from related article texts in several cut-and-paste operations, which he often supplied with new, handwritten transitions and revised page numbers. This accounts for the many folders that can only be categorized as fragments, drafts, and notes. Sections from his scholarly writing, published and unpublished, were also frequently repurposed for his graduate seminar lectures.
  German Baroque Literature. The material filed here pertains specifically to the writing and production of the two volumes of the catalogue, German Baroque Literature (Yale University Press, 1958 and 1966), but is closely related to the (generally earlier) material filed with Faber's personal papers documenting his activity as a collector. Faber's text for German Baroque Literature, vol.1, written in German, was translated into English by Yale librarian, editor, translator, and scholar Leon Nemoy (1901-98), who retired from Yale in 1966 as Curator of Hebrew and Arabic Literature. (The library legend that Leon Nemoy was Mr. Spock's uncle needs confirmation: the names are spelled differently: Nemoy/Nimoy.)
  Arranged largely in chronological order according to date of publication.
  - Deutsche Barocklyrik. Eine Auswahl aus der Zeit von 1620-1720. (Salzburg, Leipzig: A Pustet, 1936)
    - Reviews. Typed transcriptions, 1 clipping (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tausend Jahre deutsche Dichtung (with Kurt Wolff.) (New York: Pantheon, 1949), 1946
    - Introduction: various drafts, complete and fragmentary (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Table of contents: various drafts (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Poem texts: typed, printed paste-ups, handwritten (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - "Ruhmestafel": various drafts (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - First line index (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - German Baroque Literature. A Catalog of the Collection in the Yale University Library Volume 1 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1958)
    - Early draft, in German, partially in alphabetical order, ms. & typescript pages (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Notes and drafts showing Faber's work in organizing the book into chapters (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Complete draft, in German, with introduction, ms. & typescript (Box 3, Folder 17-20)
    - Complete draft, in German, continued (Box 4, Folder 21-25)
    - Complete draft, in German, continued (Box 5, Folder 26-30)
    - Additional drafts of some sections, in German, ms. & typescript (Box 6, Folder 31-38)
    - Notes, drafts, and memoranda between Faber and the book's English translator, Leon Nemoy (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Preface & introduction, English, corrected typescript (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Materials relating to funding, production, and marketing (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Letters received after publication. (Box 7, Folder 42)
      Correspondents include Erich Trunz, Richard Alewyn, Ernst Hauswedell, Harold Jantz, and Thornton Wilder
    - Reviews, mostly printed (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - German Baroque Literature. A Catalog of the Collection in the Yale University Library. Volume 2 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1966)
    - New acquisitions ("Neuerwerbungen für die Katalog"), ms. & typescript. (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - Interleaved copy of printed volume 1 with handwritten additions (bound vol.) (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Preparation, production, marketing (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Reviews (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Die Maske in der Dichtung des 17. Jahrhunderts
    - Introduction, autograph and typescript (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Kapitel I. Maskierte Dichtung, 3 typescripts, with fragments (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Kapitel II. Maskierung des Staates, autograph draft; typescript (2 copies, one corrected) (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Kapitel III. Ohne Larve. 2 typescripts, autograph drafts (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - [Opitz]
    - Reading notes (Box 10, Folder 52-54)
    - "Notizen zum Barockbuch" (Box 10, Folder 55)
    - Fragments on various topics: "Vesuvius; Gedichte; Theorie; Zum Barock; Judith; Hercine; Daphne" (Box 10, Folder 56)
    - "Pibrac" (Box 10, Folder 57)
    - Plan for a lecture (Box 10, Folder 58)
    - Fragments (Box 10, Folder 59)
    - "Die Zincgrefsche Ausgabe von Opitz' Gedichten" (alternate title: "Die teutschen Poemata von 1624."). Typescript, 51 p.; another draft, partly autograph; partial English translation (Box 10, Folder 60)
    - "Das Buch von der Deutschen Poeterey," 2 autograph drafts (Box 10, Folder 61)
    - "Opitz' Gedichte," fragment, typescript and autograph draft (Box 10, Folder 62)
- Graduate Courses: Lectures and Notes, 1949-1961; Series III; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Faber developed several graduate seminars at Yale, including courses on bibliography, the baroque, eighteenth-century authors, and Stefan George. He gave his baroque course several times, represented by voluminous lecture notes. Two sections of this material were labeled by him 1958/59 and 1961/62, but the greater part of the material had no such designation. These files are disorganized: drawing material from other parts of his writing and research, he seems to have fashioned it loosely into course format that evolved with each iteration of the course. This is also the case with the seminar in bibliography: portions of the material appear to have drifted forward each time the course was given. The boundary between the course on the Classical Age and the seminar on Hölderlin is similarly porous.
  - Course proposals (Box 11, Folder 63)
  - Aufklärung. (Box 11, Folder 64-65)
  - Barock. (Box 11, Folder 66-69)
  - Bibliographie. (Box 12, Folder 70)
    Undated folder of lists and notes, including a perhaps unrelated notebook labeled "Pritschmeister." The following two folders were originally nested in this one.
  - Bibliographie, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 71)
    Notes, lists, typed mid-year examination dated 26 January 1958, and a notebook labeled "Taillefer. Reinschrift," partly about Uhland's ballad.
  - Bibliographie, 1960-1961 (Box 12, Folder 72)
    A larger amount of material, including two autograph drafts of a long essay entitled "Einleitung in die Literaturwissenschaft," one dated October 1947
  - [Bibliographie] Nachschlagewerke, Bibliographien, Zeitschriften. 3. Vorlesung. Reinschrift. (Box 12, Folder 73)
  - Eschatologische Dichtung (Box 12, Folder 74)
    Notes on Gryphius, Balde, Angelus Silesius and others – appears to be set up as a semester course, but could be a book or essay plan.
  - German Poetry of the Classical Age, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 75)
  - Hölderlin (Box 12, Folder 76)
    This material is not in good order, but contains a class signup list and appeared to be organized into separate lectures with paper clips.
  - Klassische Dichtung, 1954-1955 (Box 12, Folder 77)
  - Ode und Elegie, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 78)
  - Stefan George (Box 13, Folder 79)
    The course may have been called George and Hofmannsthal, given in 1956 and probably in 1948.
  - Sturm und Drang (Box 13, Folder 80)
- Articles, Lectures, and Research Notes by Topic, 1946-1960; Series IV; 2.1; (5 boxes)
  The texts and drafts filed here reflect Faber's broad learning in European literature. Many of the articles relate to particular materials in the Yale Collection of German Literature.
  Hofmannsthal. Faber wrote two essays on Hofmannsthal: (1) "Der Abstieg in den Berg. Zu Hofmannsthals "Bergwerk zu Falun," which appeared in Monatshefte 43 (1951), and (2) a lecture given at Columbia. There are several interrelated drafts, in both German and English, on Hofmannsthal, as well as a mass of odd pages and notes, likely the product of recycling one essay into another. The archived versions of the Monatshefte article are longer than what was finally printed.
  Khuen. Faber's paper on the little-known Bavarian poet and composer Johann Khuen (1606-75) appeared in 1949 in PMLA 64:4. Based largely on the scarce copies of Khuen's works in Faber's own collection, the article includes a bibliography of works attributed to Khuen. (NB: the Yale Orbis system lists Johann Khuen as Johannes Kuen.)
  Moscherosch. Faber's article on Moscherosch, with the title "Philander, der Geängstigte, und der Expertus Robertus," was published twice, first in volume 39 of Monatshefte (1947) and a decade later, in revised form, in Euphorion as "Johann Michael Moscherosch, der Geängstigte" (vol. 51:3, 1957). It was also submitted to PMLA in 1946 or 1947. The collection includes a mass of handwritten notes and drafts, several typescripts, proof from Euphorion, a few pieces of relevant correspondence, and reader reports. The Moscherosch files also include a segment of Faber's drafts on the topic of Renaissance, reflecting his interpretation of Moscherosch as a writer with deep roots in the sixteenth century.
  - 1350-1600 [Notes on Early Modern Literature] (Box 14, Folder 81)
  - "The Ackermann aus Böhmen," typescript (Box 14, Folder 82)
  - "Angelus Silesius," autograph manuscript, 2 versions. Another version in typescript. (Box 14, Folder 83)
    Introduction to a selection from Der cherubinische Wandersmann translated by Willard R. Trask and published by Pantheon Books in 1953. With two letters from Kurt Wolff.
  - [Arnim, Bettina von] "Goethe und Bettina von Arnim. Ein neuer Fund," autographs and typescripts, at least two versions, with correspondence. PMLA 75:3 (1960) (Box 14, Folder 84)
  - "Die Atriden in der europäischen Literatur," autograph notes and drafts; autograph ms., 2 typescripts (Box 14, Folder 85)
  - [Atriden] "The family of Atreus in European Literature," labeled "Vortrag Englisch und Artikel. Englisch," 2 typescripts, one in 2 copies (Box 14, Folder 86)
  - "Die Bedeutung und das Wesen einer Erstausgabensammlung," typescript, with a handwritten English version (Box 14, Folder 87)
  - [Bohemian Brethren]. "The earliest hymnal of the Bohemian Brethren," typescript. YULG 23:4 (April 1949): 190-93. With correspondence. (Box 14, Folder 88)
  - [Broch] "Der Seelenführer in Hermann Brochs Tod des Vergil." Several drafts and printed version from Wächter und Hüter. Festschrift für Hermann J. Weigand (New Haven, 1957), 147-61 (Box 14, Folder 89)
  - [Broch] Lecture on Broch, reworked from parts of the above. With an ANS from Hermann J. Weigand, 22 Feb. 1946 (Box 14, Folder 90)
  - [Croce] Reading notes in a spiral notebook (Box 14, Folder 91)
  - "Die drei Stufen der Barocklyrik," autograph ms. and notes, with a list: "Themen für Columbia University" (Box 14, Folder 92)
  - [George] "Stefan George et le symbolisme français," autograph ms. and 3 typescripts, representing lecture version and the version printed in Comparative Literature V:2 (1953) (Box 14, Folder 93)
  - "The German Literature Collection," autograph ms. and 2 typescripts. YULG 38:4 (Box 14, Folder 94)
  - Goethe bicentennial: lists, notes, etc., 1949/49 (Box 15, Folder 95)
  - [Goethe] "Der Erstdruck des Faustfragments," 4 slightly different typescripts and print version from Monatshefte 41 (1949). (Box 15, Folder 96-97)
    With two related papers, at least one of which appears to be by Carl F. Schreiber, with correspondence and notes suggesting a planned Speck Collection publication to include both papers.
  - [Goethe] "Georg Oswald May's portraits of Goethe and Wieland," 4 typescripts. YULG 31:1 (1956). (Box 15, Folder 98)
    These are the portraits that hang in the north corridor of the Beinecke Library, court level.
  - [Goethe] "Goethe's first book," autograph ms. and typescript YULG 32:1 (1957) (Box 15, Folder 99)
  - "Goethe, impulse and harmony," typescript, 19 p. (probably a lecture) (Box 15, Folder 100)
  - [Goethe] "The reception of Goethe's poems in the English-speaking world," typescript, with partial autograph ms. in German (Box 15, Folder 101)
  - "Grimmelshausen Vortrag," autograph manuscript in spiral notebook (Box 15, Folder 102)
  - [Gryphius] "Andreas Gryphius, der Rebell," autograph ms., 2 typescripts (Box 15, Folder 103)
  - [Gryphius] "Andreas Gryphius, der Rebell," final typescript, proof. PMLA 74:1 (1959) (Box 15, Folder 104)
  - [Hesse] "Zu Hermann Hesses 'Glasperlenspiel,'" autograph ms. and two different typescripts. Monatshefte 40:4 (1948) (Box 15, Folder 105)
  - [Hofmannsthal] "Der Abstieg in den Berg. Zu Hofmannsthals Bergwerk zu Falun," 2 typescripts and manuscript; printed version from Monatshefte 43 (1951) (Box 15, Folder 106)
  - [Hofmannsthal]. Drafts, fragments, notes, largely autograph and in German, relating to the above (Box 16, Folder 107)
  - [Hofmannsthal]. "The all-powerful spirit: A study of Hofmannsthal's Bergwerk zu Falun." Another version entitled "Descent into the Mountain." Typescripts (Box 16, Folder 108)
  - [Hofmannsthal] "Hofmannsthal und der Begriff der dichterischen Wahrheit," autograph ms., in spiral notebook (Box 16, Folder 109)
  - [Hofmannsthal] Notes and drafts about his correspondence with Richard Beer-Hofmann, Hermann Bahr, and Arthur Schnitzler (these letters are part of YCGL) (Box 16, Folder 110)
  - "Der katholische Beitrag zur Dicthung des 17. Jahrhunderts," autograph manuscript (Box 16, Folder 111)
  - [Khuen] Research notes and drafts for the paper on Johann Khuen (Box 16, Folder 112-114)
  - [Kheun] "Johann Khuen," autograph ms. (Box 16, Folder 115)
  - [Kheun] "Johann Khuen," 2 typescript drafts (Box 16, Folder 116)
  - [Kheun] "Johann Khuen," (final?) typescript. PMLA 64:4 (1949) (Box 16, Folder 117)
  - [Kühlmann] "Die Keimzeller des Kühlpsalters." Offprint from JEGP 46:2 (1947), annotated by FdF (Box 16, Folder 118)
  - Lecture proposals and outlines, autograph drafts (Box 16, Folder 119)
  - Miscellaneous notes and fragments, some on his Italian stationery (Box 16, Folder 120)
  - [Mann, Thomas] "Dr. Faustus," autograph manuscript (Box 17, Folder 121)
  - "Monarch, patron and poet," notes and fragments (Box 17, Folder 122)
  - "Monarch, patron and poet," first draft, in German, "Dichter und Mäzen in 17. Jahrhundert" (Box 17, Folder 123)
  - "Monarch, patron and poet," German version, autograph ms. and typescript (Box 17, Folder 124)
  - "Monarch, patron and poet," English version, typescript. Germanic Review (1949) (Box 17, Folder 125)
  - [Moscherosch] Autograph notes and drafts (Box 17, Folder 126)
  - [Moscherosch] "Philander, der Geängstigte," 2 typescripts, draft on the renaissance, correspondence with PMLA (Box 17, Folder 127)
  - [Moscherosch] "Johann Michael Moscherosch, der Geängstigte," 2 typescripts, proof, correspondence with Euphorion (Box 17, Folder 128)
  - [Opitz] "Der Aristarchus: Eine Neuwertung," early version, mostly autograph; typed draft; [final?] typescript; correspondence relating to publication. PMLA 69:3 (1954) (3 folders) (Box 17, Folder 129-131)